Hi, everybody.
Almost completed the.
Language itself. I mean,
so far we basically explored a number of
things. We explored the.
Programming languages,
construct semantics,
complicated constructs and everything.
All these are, uh, required, uh,
to be able to understand the code
generated by the AI, we said.
So that's part of the game.
Now we start,
which is basically the last part of the
course we will.
Start also having some exercise together
trying to.
Uh.
To do uh.
Both project examples and also exercise
on how to do things I was thinking to.
Try to develop a a system in a couple of
hour together,
collaborating and using the AI to develop
a full application.
And then from the content standpoint,
we we now start looking not at the
language itself, but.
At the language plus the runtime,
we already had a run into the CLR as an
example of a sophisticated runtime,
but we are left with concurrent
programming.
Which is clearly not part of this course
in the broader notion of concurrency,
but in the last 10 years,
PROGRAMMING languages have evolved.
Introducing asynchronous PROGRAMMING and
we have to understand what are the
implication in terms of runtime we we
will have some.
Run into debugging.
Because you know what?
We also need to talk about debugging,
testing.
In testing blah blah.
Um.
And interoperability,
which we barely touched,
I mean so far what we said about
interoperability,
we said we need contracts, OK.
So at the end of the day if you think at
the.
Form of the activation record that that's
a contract. I mean,
there are possible choices.
We can layout variables in one order on
the opposite.
The stack can be cleaned by the caller or
by the colleague,
so there are options and usually in our
discipline when there are options,
we need conventions,
otherwise the system will not work.
And so the that is the very minimum
example of interoperability across
systems.
And is the core.
But today we will spend some time in
talking about.
I already mentioned it honestly,
but I was very, very,
very quick and it was OK when I was.
Introducing the ideas today,
we will spend the day talking about
marshalling and unmarshalling.
And markup languages, OK.
So first of all,
what are markup languages?
Someone what is a markup language?
Example of our markup languages.
Hmm XML. Another one. XDM another one.
I made yes, Markdown, Jason.
There is the uh.
TSON. This is a new one.
How many have heard about TSON?
You have to stay ahead of time.
This one has been just announced by
Hugging Face and this stands for token.
OK, so it's a sort of Jason,
but with less tokens because actually
we're spending a lot because to pass the
eye.
The structured data we pay a lot of
commas and syntax restriction in coming
from Jason and so TSON is the new.
Big markup out there to save tokens when
we send data to the AI.
At least that's expressions.
All the parentheses.
Remember in least where you have this
everything is a least.
The least that means made of atoms and
parentheses. That's a markup line, OK.
So all these examples,
what tells us about markup languages?
So what is the difference between?
A PROGRAMMING language and a markup
language.
Oh,
everyone here has used mark up languages.
Show data.
I mean, it's it's a point of view,
but it's not complete. What is it?
So can I?
Execute the HTML.
I see the web page.
But no, yes, you cannot execute.
So basically the markup language at its
core is a formal syntax.
To which you can write a parser,
and the difference is that it's just a
formal formal syntax to represent.
Uh, some data.
Without having a predefined semantics
attached to the language.
So it has the formality,
the formalism of the formal language
without having the semantics of its
execution.
OK, so no,
HTML is not a PROGRAMMING language,
as many students believe,
and the purpose of these languages is
basically annotate data with the.
With semantics,
which I understand that that is
counterintuitive,
but basically the semantics of the tags.
So any markup language basically takes
test and annotates part of the test with
some.
Sign in JSON it's a dictionary taken from
JavaScript.
In XML it's the name of the target which
establish.
Some meaning,
but the meaning it's not defined in the
in the language in the in the markup
language itself, it's outside.
So if I use title clearly means that the
text between the open title and close
title.
Is the the the the meaning of the of the
data,
but the title tag is not part of the XML
definition. Yes, JavaScript part of the.
JavaScript is a PROGRAMMING language,
but JavaScript is not.
It's embedded in some elements of HTML.
So HTML can contain JavaScript.
JavaScript is a PROGRAMMING language,
but HTML is not a PROGRAMMING language.
So domestic.
It may contain can contain JavaScript,
but it's specification does not contain
how to interpret JavaScript exactly and
to be honest the script element in.
In in in HTML allows you to specify the
scripted language because there was a
time in which you can say type equal VB
and on Windows you can have.
Visual basis scripts inside the web page
and it was working.
So technically HTML is just the container
and through the element you tell this
payload is JavaScript.
And this is so true to the point in which
we now have TypeScript or other languages
that are not even available in the
browser and there are rewriting system
that are low time.
Rewrite the main data structure of the
web browser, which is.
What is the main data structure of web
browser?
No, the document object model, right?
Why? Because at the end of the day,
any data structure that is induced by the
type system we studied so far is a tree.
And if you need to represent a graph,
basically you have a monitor,
you have a pointer to some other part of
the tree,
and in this way we present the graph.
At the end of the day,
the data structure is mainly a tree.
As it is objects, fields, objects, fields.
That's a tree. OK, and if you if you want,
you can.
And for sure the browser is a good place
to look for.
You will know that if you going into F12
which is the debugger which is available
in pretty much any.
Web browser you can actually browse the
tree that is represented by the markup.
And so you can call ups back,
I mean change the web page and and other
things.
And my cap has become more and more
import, so from an historical standpoint.
From a an historical standpoint.
There we are.
Uh.
Outline.
Uh.
Briefly important moments in markup.
Language evolution.
And history.
Let me see what?
Our AI friend is able to do.
OK, so Goldfarb,
I already mentioned it at some point,
if you remember introduced the S,
the GML and then the SGML,
the standardized general markup.
Language notation. So it's a very,
very old idea. Yes, Jamal is from the 86.
The problem with the SGML,
it was that it was too abstract, right?
Because basically OK,
I annotate with tags the my data.
And So what?
Because you can't decide the name of the
tag or technically of the element.
Uh,
and decide the meaning for every
different document, which is nice,
but at the end of the day it's not so
useful. Um, at CERN.
Tim Berners-Lee had the idea of using the
SGML syntax because there was already an
SGML package available for Linux back
then and also for Unix.
had the idea to use the SGML syntax to
represent the hypertext markup language
and so basically HTML fixed
The meaning of the tags.
So it is just an instance of this broader
concept of generalized markup syntax.
Um.
And then we got 969798 XML extensible
markup language which we still know and
use,
but it's not so popular because now it's
considered.
2 variables as a syntax,
but when I was at your post 20 years ago
it was super cool XML and actually.
I even contributed to G.
Um.
Uh.
To a package for the new software
foundation that was called simple XML as
XML.
Because it was and it was then when I
first.
Start the contributing to the Uh.
To the Uh new free software Uh Foundation
Uh.
Software and actually I had the.
Defining the translation of pre software
in Italian, which is the software liver.
We were appointed for translating the
main document of pre software foundation.
Actually we were asked to review the
translation.
We got an Italian translation.
That was made by a non-technical person.
And so Richard Stillman contacted us to
ask for reviewing this and we said
Richard,
honestly this is not can be published
publicate and so we we have offered for
free of course.
To do the the the translation.
And actually Richard told us yes,
but I know you Italians,
you have to translate free software
because you have the privilege to have a
language that allows you.
To distinguish between free as in beer or
free as in freedom,
as they used to say and so,
but I know that you Italians you like to
use English terms,
so please free software should be
translated.
I think I still have all the debate we
had. We were, of course, super. OK,
we were, of course, super.
Thrilled that Richard Stalman was talking
to us.
And so we spend a lot debating and
eventually we landed into the software
libero definition, which I mean.
Looking now, it was fairly obvious,
but back then it wasn't that much.
And so there was an Apple J book that was
published with this translation and and
and and I was part of the team because I
did contribute with the simple XML.
Stuff that I did develop that was a
program that they basically use it to
mark expand the XML tags.
The website of the computer science
department that was implemented using
that that package at some point. OK,
as you can see.
At some point the simply lightweight
markup languages started to emerge and
now we get we have JSON, we have the YAML,
et cetera, et cetera,
and we have to live with this.
So there are several things that must be
said about markup languages.
So markup by definition.
So once someone talking about XML set,
I mean XML is only.
A verbose way to express Lisp as
expressions. OK,
because it is a way to give the name in
Lisp.
Basically when you have an S expression
you you type in.
It's not just open brace,
it is open brace name atom one, atom two,
close the brace.
OK and if I want to have a sub tree.
I will say name 2A2A3 and this is a
subtree. OK so in XML.
These.
Let me do it here.
In XML I will write something like name.
Hey, you wanna?
Name 2A2.
I three this is a potential
representation close name name two and
close it name right?
So at the end of the day someone
commented this is just a way to have a
verbose closing.
Parentheses. OK,
so that's a characteristic of every
markup language.
You need to be able to represent a tree.
So I have no memory of markup languages
that are linear.
OK,
and the other trait is that the the text
is structured and annotated with some
meta annotation.
So there is clearly a meta language.
Which is in this case name is not part of
the text.
There is an annotation on top of the text.
So it's not part of the content,
it's a meta content and and then there is
the content. OK, so that's basically.
The way the world is divided into and why
the markup language?
And become, uh, so popular.
Markup languages have become so popular
because of writing parses,
as you I I hope you know by now,
it's really annoying. I mean,
it's not difficult in itself once you got
the grammar.
The context grammar theory and tokenizing
and you know tokenize it parses all the
things we introduced at the very
beginning of the course.
Reality is that it's just an unknowing
work because you have to go into the
details and and if the language is.
Slightly complicated.
You have to write a lot of productions,
verify that the grammar is can be parsed,
etc.
But most of the data that we deal with
today.
Are basically trees. I mean,
if I open a an HTML document,
that's clearly a tree.
If I take a Word document, that's a tree.
Basically it's similar to HTML and it's
that if you want to take a spreadsheet,
it can be represented.
As a tree. OK,
so most of the data can be labeled using
the the tree notation and therefore
people start saying,
but why should we introduce new formats
all the time where we can use?
The markup syntax and save the time of
writing a parser.
And So what made XML popular was the
availability of XML parsers in all the
main programming languages java.net.
CC all these languages came with the
parses. OK,
so whenever you see a markup language.
Or a markdown.
So I think that the markdown we will
spend a few minutes later to talk about
markdown because markdown is a nice
example of.
He then closing parenthesis. I mean,
so it still is a tree,
but it's he then to simplify the writing
because we are annoyed.
It is annoying to write and also reading
the the the the XML.
But going back to those days, everybody,
everybody.
One was thrilled because for the first
time we had we could write programs
without having to write parses in every
different program. Before then,
I mean if you look at Office,
Office 97 was using the doc format.
It was property and it was a binary
format and they had to.
To write and maintain the parser of the
doc file. You know how docx files work.
Don't you? You know you have. Have you?
Did you ever open a docx file?
Is a zip file. Is a is a zip file.
So let's make an example.
Because most of the day it will be spent
on XML because it's the older and it's
also more capable. It's also annoying,
but it's more capable.
So.
I advanced program.
OK, save the document.
Browser.
Example.
All right, so now I have the example so.
Example.
If I open it with the seven.
This is the word format with ODT is
exactly the same.
There was a debate about which XML should
be used to represent documents,
so eventually.
Unfortunately,
Microsoft used its own power,
financial power to have in the ISO
committee a double standard.
So ODT files were already standardized
and then Microsoft pushed the.
Also to standardize the docx format.
So basically now we have two different
standard formats available. OK, let me.
Let me, uh, extract the.
All right.
Let me so um.
As you can see there are files and these
files have standard names that are
defined somewhere.
So if I open this it appears.
Fairly obvious why XML is dead.
You spend most of the time in trying to
understand where the an element starts
and when what what contains without an
editor is.
Barely browseable and so it's complicated.
Here we can find the document and a lot
of things and eventually there will be
high.
And then advance it and then rogrammers.
Very easy.
OK, but every single place of this format.
Has a meaning and you have to understand
why things have become so complicated,
because typically we programmers,
we don't like complicated things.
So when you.
Our student, you say, oh, come on, I mean,
should I learn all this thing?
Let's use JSON, OK?
And when people started using JSON,
it was much simpler, much readable, etc.
And then someone said.
But how can we check that the JSON file
is properly formatted?
Because I need to type check the the
document,
otherwise my program will not work.
In XML you have a full standard that
allows you to automatically check.
The syntax of a particular XML dialect in
JSON. You don't. I've got an idea.
Let's have JSON schema OK and you start
complicating JSON and eventually some
other student will.
You grow with this as you don't feel the
complexity and then some other student.
20 years from now we'll come here and say,
come on, Jason is too complicated.
I need a simpler one and you start it
again and we keep.
And it's a way of natural evolution of
programming languages.
But it's important to understand XML
because it is probably the largest
superset of markup languages available.
Today and every other language is simply
a simplified version of this,
apart from the syntax that we just
learned that it was defined in during the
60s in a world in which where the
computing.
Was completely different.
So can anyone tell me what is?
What is XML? I mean XML is a standard.
That's easy.
And what? What? What defines?
Another attempt.
It defines a syntax and what are the
constituents of this syntax?
O notice it defines.
Syntax.
Uh.
The the syntax, but is extensible.
So in the example of the name or even
here this document which is the name of
this element.
Basically is um.
Uh is not defined in the XML.
In the XML said OK, there are elements.
Elements have a names and the name is not
defined in the standard is part of the
definition of the of of the user is not
part of the standard.
So extensible is there are no fixed names,
attributes and everything so.
OK,
what are the two main constituents of XML?
Well, you you actually wrote.
So it's a man in your life, so.
Tags and content, but no, that's.
I mean there are tags,
but in the definition of the language
there are no tags.
Actually there are elements,
so the two main constituents.
Oh, an XML documents are.
Elements.
And another one.
No.
Attributes are art of the elements.
There is another one.
Yeah, content. OK, so three.
There is another one apart from content.
No,
that's part of the definition of the
entities. What are entities?
Have you ever seen something like?
This in an HTML file.
Ampersand A grade.
Have you ever seen it?
In HTML is has been used to define.
Uh, OK, so.
That is. So entities are elements.
Let's make an example of an element.
An element is opened by a tag.
So that's the reason,
because tags are constituents, yes,
but are part of the definition of the
element.
So if you write the grammar of the XML.
You have the roduction element and the
element has opening tag.
The content and the closing tag or an
element can be C data.
C data stands for character data. OK,
so the element has a name.
It may have attribute attributes.
Attributes are specified like this.
And then a content.
And then?
The element is caused by A tag written
like slash name of the tag or if the
content is empty there is a a compact
version which is.
This one.
So if the element has no content,
you simply write the tag and you use
slash right angle bracket to close the
tag, right?
So these are the two main constituents of
an HT of an XML file.
HTML is not XML.
Why one example?
No, that that will be corrected data.
We can represent it.
There is a single. There are several,
but I mean there is an easy one.
Have you ever?
Seen our page like this which contains
the RBRBR.
Yes, and that's the break, you know,
you know.
A new line in HTML.
Do you see closing break closing here? No.
And that was and still is acceptable for
HTML,
but that's not valid XML because there is
no closing element.
At some point,
because of course browser works anyway,
but it was useful to be able to quickly
parse an HTML file,
so that there's been a strong attempt.
To push XHTML which was basically a
redefinition of X of HTML that was fully
XML compliant.
So to avoid these quirks like these
single tags without content and.
These day you may often find like this,
which makes it fully XML compliant at the
HTML. OK,
but the original HTML is not fully XML.
OK, so.
6.
Let me go back to our document.
OK.
In fact,
there there are other directives that the
standard XML assumes.
Among those you find the the first
annotation which informs that the file
contains XML content and it is defined by
a tag which is opened by.
Uh, left angle bracket,
question mark and it is closed by
question mark, right angle bracket. OK,
so basically that is.
An instance of another constituent that I
omitted because it's not related to the
document itself,
but if you find the AB equals C, whatever.
Uh.
What is eat there?
Anyone has an idea what is the meaning of
these special flags inside XML?
And those are processor directives.
So basically it is a way to tell to the
XML processor,
which is the program responsible for
parsing and processing the XML.
You can give directions.
To this OK and this is part of the
standard. So the standards say OK,
an XML is made of elements, entities,
C character data and processor directives.
OK,
and these are clearly not so popular
because these are not standard and
basically it's a way to tell.
If you don't understand the process of
this, ignore it.
It's not part of the document,
it's just a way. Oh, by the way,
I also forgot another,
which is the comment.
But that's easy.
OK.
OK, but let's go back to this thing,
because if I take this,
which is actually valid XML document,
there are apparently other constituent
that I didn't talk about.
For instance here this element now see
not that this this is it opens the
document element.
It has this colon W colon.
Anyone knows the syntax?
How do we parse this thing?
And is it part of the Linda XML standard?
No, it's not.
So actually this is an XML valid document
and if I look it from XML itself.
This is the name of the element.
I mean the column has no meaning for XML.
It's just a character like anyone else,
but clearly here it's used with some
meaning. OK,
So what is the meaning of this?
Column in attribute names or.
Uh, element names.
Anyone knows that?
Name please. Thank you.
Actually there is another specification
which sits on top of XML which is known
as XMLMS namespaces,
which basically tells OK if you have a
valid.
If you you can take a valid XML document,
but if you use names of elements or
attributes using the column,
this is the meaning and it's really.
Pretty key to understand. Oh, why?
First of all,
why do we need the namespaces?
Because we started tagging the whole
world during the 90s and and we found
quickly that my definition of title was
different from Andrea's definition of
title.
And so how can we insert annotate a
document with both definition initials AC?
Yeah, another question.
So the solution was OK,
we need namespaces.
Namespaces in the way are defined in
programming languages are not so easily.
Implemented in XML.
So imagine a word in which we were trying
to tag everything.
I mean Word documents are the result of
this process of those years.
So basically the idea was can we do
something as we did with the URL?
URLs.
The URLs were so genius because they
allow to represent everything,
any resource with any protocol,
etcetera in with the same syntax schema.
Can we do the similar thing with
documents so we can mix things together?
Yes,
namespace play a fundamental role and
they are really counterintuitive because
namespaces in XML are bound to the
element.
So basically there are no namespace
global namespaces.
Technically they are in the element and
it is even more counterintuitive.
So this is one of the trickiest syntax I
know of.
When I want to test someone the
understanding of of formal languages,
I often use this to make questions
because.
Basically.
This is the name.
Notice that W is not defined here.
I mean there is no W before.
What is the this W where it is defined?
So they said OK to introduce a namespace.
In an element,
so this means that the scope of that
namespace is the element itself plus the
content.
So all the subtree you introduce an
attribute whose prefix is XMLNS.
Then the colon and then the name of the
namespace.
So technically this attribute defines the
WPC namespace.
OK and the namespace is defined by a Uri.
Uniform resource identifier.
What is the difference between the URI
and UL?
Basically, yes, I mean also you're,
I mean syntactically they are the same.
The difference is that you and I may not
not exist.
OK,
it's just the name that uses the URL
syntax, but it may not not exist.
It's just an identifier. OK,
because we proved that that this syntax
is case worldwide and helps you to
understand who's in charge.
So in this case.
From the URL we know that this is
Microsoft of this word.
So basically it is very informative as a
syntax and so the the URI says OK,
Microsoft should not have a web page with
that URL. It's OK.
It's just an identifier to tell this is
the organization, this is the application,
etcetera, etcetera. OK,
so it's just a unique identifier
worldwide.
And so adding names if you want to scale
up to the world will not work. So we say,
OK, let's introduce.
Basically aliases. So inside this element,
WPC stands for HTTP blah blah blah OK,
that's the first important aspect.
And this is counterintuitive because here
here this is the namespace that I'm using.
So this is this is the element document
as intended in the namespace W.
And now if I want to understand what is
WI look for XMLNSW equal.
OK,
and as you can see the W is not a
Microsoft schema,
but it is openxmlformats.org schema,
so it's part of the standard.
So all the W.
Target elements and attributes are part
of the standards,
the rest may be just Microsoft related or
something. OK,
so as you can see it is very flexible but
at the same time.
It complicates dramatically the syntax of
XML because XML in itself it was very
very clean.
But then as soon as we need to give some
not really semantics,
you're saying OK W document as.
As the open XML formats intends to be. OK,
so basically you're not formally saying
what is the semantics of the document
element,
you're saying document as intended by
this organization.
Right,
because we said that the markup languages
contains data and not semantics and not
the ability to execute OK.
Right.
Can you give me an example?
Of a day.
OK, XML.
Document.
This things.
Let literally inflamed the humanist.
You may were all the rage because they
said, OK,
we now can annotate all the books, poems,
etcetera in our research with meta
information that are part of the document
and so.
During the 90s, at the end of the 90s,
they came up with the pay XML syntax
where as you can see there is the header,
the statement, the title, the author,
the editor, the publication, etcetera,
etcetera.
And they define a number of standard tags.
Now how can I formally verify that this
particular XML is in fact K compliant?
Because if I take the XML syntax
definition,
the XML syntax definition simply says OK,
I check it. There are elements,
there are see data,
there are everything is there are
entities, ampersand, content, column.
So everything is in there. XML is valid.
That's OK.
But actually that's not enough because I
want to I I'm not interested in to check
whether this is XML compliant.
Now I'm interested in understanding
whether the syntax of the tags of the
elements,
the way you nest the elements together.
Satisfy a sort of a higher level syntax,
which is how you can compose elements to
have a meaningful document that can be
automatically processed.
Um, the first um.
The first attempt to capture this thing
was part of the original XML
specification.
Uh, give.
Me an example of DTD.
For day.
Sure.
We complete.
So the original XML definition introduced
the document template definition,
which is part of the standard.
Which is basically a way to declare how
you.
So I can define templates of documents
and say, OK,
the title element should be inside the
header. OK, that's basically the goal.
So to give not only the syntax,
the character syntax of the tags,
etcetera, but also how?
Can you combine the elements of a
particular document? That was the DTD and.
And this is an example.
So as you can see of course it uses the
angle brackets for working and there are.
The element.
So now you see that element is an
official name. In fact, you define. Yeah,
there is an element which is called Tay,
which is made of a Tay header followed by
text.
And then the day header is a file desk
and then the file desk is a title
statement followed by publication
statement followed by source desk.
So basically it is a grammar of elements.
How you can combine elements together to
obtain a value.
The TE document,
which is all the TE documents are valid
XML documents, but there are.
XML valid documents that are not a valid
document.
OK and and so that's and you know what
you can define PC data is character data
and and and it's so the editor is data.
That's it.
Of course there are also the attribute,
the attributes, so you can basically.
Define a list of attributes for the
element RS, which is the type.
The type can be one of these values and
its value is implied by.
The so in the so in the RS element I can
use the attribute type and I can say
either person, object,
place or organization, no other values.
So you can determine not only the syntax
of how you.
Mix things together,
but also how the attributes are defined
and what we what are the valid attributes
for a specific for a for a specific.
Tame late document and it seemed a good
start. In fact it was.
As long as you define the documents such
as the metadata for you for books.
But.
It was fairly natural to think that you
would like to be able to represent a
programmable object, I mean.
It will be nice to be able to serialize a
tree of objects in the memory of my
program down to XML syntax. Why? Oh,
I can save the state of my application
and.
I can parse it back, uh, later without,
you know, writing a parser.
At the end of the day, that's the reason.
Um.
Anyone of you has an idea of when in your
life the application you use have to save
the state and restore the state all the
time?
Because it's a fairly important process,
the ability to persist the state of
application and you use it every day and
probably you don't even know it.
So in your application when.
The state of the application is saved and
restored without you saving.
In the mobile applications,
because to save resources,
the application is informed. Look,
I'm about to terminate you.
So since you want to give the user the
impression that the application is still
running.
We don't have enough resources to keep it
running because I'm on the phone.
You know what? I'm going to kill you.
But if you save your state and then you
restore the state,
the impression for the user is that the
application is always running,
even if it's not.
So serialized and deserialized data
structure is something that all our
system do all the time. OK,
mobile phone phones every time you switch
the application and then the operating
system decides to kill the process to
save resources.
That is a situation in which you need to
take all the objects that represent the
state of your of your application,
say onto some data store and then restore.
So this process is called serialization.
So you take the objects into the memory,
which are laid out as we know by now by
the runtime of the programming language,
and you transform into data,
and this process basically consists in
writing.
Some syntax and then you want to be able
to invert this process.
Of course there are objects that can be
serialized.
Example an example of an object that
cannot be serialized.
Hmm.
Pointers to the memory, yes,
because I mean you can of course save the
address.
Hmm.
The the the recourse definition can be
dealt with because basically you can
assign an ID.
To to the to the serialized object and
then introduce a reference to to that ID.
So this can be done but file files.
If you have an open file you have to
reopen it because actually the open file
for the for the process is the ID that
the.
Operating system gave you to present that
file,
but that is just for that particular
execution,
so it's totally pointless to serialize a
file descriptor that you've got with open.
So.
So this is civilization.
It's a very important process and.
There are other application.
I mean mobile is really a big one and so
I I I I can stop there so.
You know how much it takes in terms of
computing to simulate the structure.
So ENI, you know, the oil and gas company,
Italian.
They go and they acquire data.
So basically they insert dynamite on the
ground.
They they make the dynamite explode.
They have a lot of sensors and they
basically do the eco.
Resonance to the to the ground looking
for petrol or gas or whatever. OK,
you know how much computing it takes to
reconstruct the images given this raw
data.
Months.
So you start a competition today and you
will get a result by August.
Do you think it is affordable to have a
crash in the application?
Not really.
So just to keep up with the some memories,
when I was working with Ferrari Formula
One, the they had at some point in the.
Dynamics simulation of the car.
In that case the jobs usually run for
seven days and in the new cluster.
Back then the technical sponsor of
Ferrari was Acer and in the new cluster.
Randomly, after 5-6 days,
the job crashed and no one had an idea of
how to fix this. Ferrari was, of course,
super upset.
Ace didn't know how to do or what to do,
and so eventually came to us asking for
help to reproduce the problem. So we were.
We were running a cluster very similar to
the one they were using in Maranello and
we started testing and it took us a very
hot August.
So actually we were having a cluster of
128.
Node to simulate and we had to test the
memory.
So I spent the summary in changing memory
modules in 128 servers.
And and we flew to AMD because processor
CPUs were from AMD and and eventually
found out that it was the memory modules.
So by changing the brand of memory.
We fixed the problem because AM D is not
so good at giving electrical
specification on the board and so back
then I mix memory modules were satisfying
better the specification of that
particular board.
All this just to tell you,
a computation may run longer and a crash
is not an option because you lose all the
current and the power that you spend to.
Obtain the result and if you as our
friend Antonio,
which was responsible for IT of Ferrari
back then when there was Schumacher,
use it to say every presentation from
Antonio.
Was race starts at 2:00 PM and if that
that is the mantra,
I mean no matter what race starts at 2:00
PM and you have to be there with the car
working so.
And there there there is a technique that
is often used when you write complicated
programs that is called checkpointing,
which is very similar to what happens
inside the.
Um.
Mobile phones but scaled up into the
simulation of a large thing,
so you can't save all the time gigabytes
and gigabytes of data,
just to give you an idea.
The to simulate the car,
the fluid dynamics of the car.
They use very large clusters with
thousands of CPUs and the first node,
the head node of the cluster as one
terabyte of RAM.
Because it's where you have to slice the
3D model of the car.
Then you send every piece to several
nodes and then you in in parallel those
nodes use the finite element algorithm to
simulate through the dynamics evolution.
And at every step of simulation you have
to communicate because I mean you slice
the car, but the car in reality is.
So when you slice the all the food
dynamics interference between 2 zones
should should talk.
OK.
And so at every step of the simulation
you have to communicate the results so
that the the simulation is equivalent to
go together.
So you use low latency fabric so that you
can.
Simulate.
You don't have to wait too much between
one loop of simulation and this and this.
And so in all this complexity,
being able to serialize the relevant
state of the application so that you can
restart in case of crash is another
application.
Uh.
Another national application is to be
able to serialize a data structure that
you want to pass to a remote service.
So I don't know, I have the Geo.
Reference at the service,
which is a remote service that given IP
gives you back the region,
the geographical location of the.
It's a reasonable I pay someone else to
give me the service in my applications
and my application has to send.
The method invocation to a remote
processor managed by a different
organization.
That is something that is not in my
memory space,
so I have to serialize all the arguments
of the particular method into a message
and then receive a return message.
Which is the response example and you
generate.
An example request response in soap.
Or up.
Unenroll student service which.
Given name and birth return student ID.
OK,
so suppose I want to have some service to
enroll students in this university.
I need to take as input as a service
student student.
The student data and I have to reply.
I mean this service reply with the
student ID because the student has been
enrolled. OK,
so all these things requires.
The ability of serialized data structure
into trees and pass them back into
structured values. So if you remember,
we didn't speak too much about this,
but I think it's important to remember it
that there are.
Several passing style of the arguments.
From the caller to the colleague,
I mean there are.
There are.
Passing styles such as by copy. OK,
so when you pass you invoke a function in
your programming language,
the value is copied,
which means that if you modify inside the
function the value of the the argument.
This change is is local to the function.
It will not be seen outside.
I think you're familiar with this another
one.
Bye, bye.
Pass by reference you pass.
At the end of the day you pass pointer to
the memory.
So basically you're allowed to manipulate
the the argument also from outside.
Are there other?
Another one was passed by name.
You basically pass the expression and the
expression will be evaluated only if
needed internally. OK, so.
But the the main two that you have to
remember are pass by value, pass by ref.
OK, so when you do marshalling,
there is no pass by ref.
OK, so you create, you clone,
you create a tree which is as the same
values of your data structure,
but which is clearly a copy of that data
structure. So when you work with.
Web services,
you're working with copies of data
structure.
So 25 years ago and I was there
unfortunately.
Our standard that was promoted that is
known as SOAP,
Simple Object Access Protocol and was
basically was a standard.
Very similar to the XML standard and XML
name space in the sense that starting
from XML gave the rules to create
messages,
request response to invoke remote.
Services. OK,
and it became really popular because
before Jason became popular,
web services were implemented using SOAP.
So it's fairly important that you know
about SOAP.
Now it's not really sexy.
It's not really the last thing.
But nevertheless,
a big part of this work world still works
using SOAP services.
So you have to be you are,
you have to be aware about this.
So as you can see, it's just an XML.
There was a SOAP envelope which included
some metadata because SOAP messages were
typically sent through HTTP requests,
but it was even possible to send them by
e-mail.
So it was possible to write an e-mail to
some endpoint with the SOAP and then
receive an e-mail with the return.
It will be, I mean,
not so efficient in terms of time
execution execution time, but.
Nevertheless, it will work.
So and then there is the body of the soap
envelope as you can see.
The namespace are defined,
so the SOAP was defined in the SOAP
namespace and then some university may
use the their own namespace to say OK,
this is my.
Student element OK and and so this is the
payload and the payload is the object
name and birth date.
OK and these are the two arguments that
in fact you're passing to the service.
On uh, the system.
Will reply with the.
The response messenger.
With some student ID and the status
enrolled.
That was basically invented by the AI,
but it's OK, it's reasonable.
And you know what?
How can we know that the reply message
for enroll student request is enroll
student response?
We need another language which is called
WSDL Web Service Definition Language.
Which by the way, is even broken.
In the sense that in Wisdom you can
define the same services,
the same service in two different ways,
which are both valid and this produces a
number of problems that you have no idea
in history, nevertheless.
OK, the definition.
So there is a message called enroll
student request and.
Because all these very long premise was
to introduce the last big guy of the XML
world, you see this type XSD string.
Or XSD in 2001 the XML.
No hype produced a monster.
And this monster was called the XML
schema XSD,
which stands for XML schema schema
definition.
The XSD is important and it was a very
ambitious project if you print in paper.
The definition of the XML schema you will
get 500 pages book.
It's a very lightweight definition,
easy to read if you want to sleep at
night and nevertheless it's really
important because the failure of DTD.
Was that it was not precise enough to
give all the details of a data structure.
It was basically impossible using
document template definition.
To express integer objects and all the
small things you need to define a data
structure. So they set and say OK,
we define DTD is not enough.
We need another standard.
Let's do XML schema.
But XML schema,
which is very annoying at the same time
is very important because it's the best
Bible we have as a as a humanity as of
today.
Which contains the sum,
the sum of all the type system of all the
programming languages.
So there are types that can be expressed
in XSD that are not expressible in
Haskell C#.
Java, OK, because basically they say OK,
this has access.
This purpose is to represent all the type
systems of all the programming languages
on this world.
So it should be a superset and and so
let's think it.
Very general. So for instance,
in XSD it is possible to express that an
array should contains at most three
elements.
Can you give me the definition in a
typical programming language in which you
can say an array of three integers?
Apart from C and C++ because you have to
allocate the the memory,
but I mean if you are in other languages
you can even say minimum two maximum time
values. OK,
so you can give ranges etcetera. So XSD.
Is very, very boring, honestly,
but at the same time it's important and
you have to know that it exists because
it's still part of the backbone of this
world and at the same time it's still the
best attempt to define a general type
system to weak.
To which you can serialize and
deserialize the structure.
So and in fact it's so good that at the
end of the day, 20 years later,
you have a Java code that generates SOAP
messages that are correctly parsed by a
Python web service that generates.
Response message in XML that is correctly
parsed back in Java. OK, so still these,
even though it's not sexy, is very,
very important because it allows to
support the marshalling and a marshalling
process for.
Interoperability in languages. OK,
so I think that for XML is much,
even too much.
Let's have a quick example of others.
I mean, so Jason,
what is the define Jason, you know?
Where Jason is defined.
What is the definition of Jason?
Hmm.
So I think it's JS schema.
I know it's json.org or something,
but let me search for it.
There is a web page online.
With the full definition of Jason,
it's there since the beginning.
That's the definition of Jason.
And it's nice because actually you get,
oh, looks like a grammar. Andrea,
we got a grammar here and and and it's
interesting because Jason uses the
JavaScript Object Notation in
unrestricted form,
which means that there are.
Valid JavaScript object that you can
write in in in JavaScript that are not
allowed by Jason itself.
For instance, in JavaScript,
it's tolerated that you don't use quotes
around the keys in the dictionaries.
In Jason,
it's mandatory to the key in the
dictionary is must be quoted and there
are many other quinks.
One of the interesting missing parts of
the Jason specification is you can't
represent the function value.
So Jason be.
In JavaScript you have the eval function
as we already commented that allows you
to take a piece of text and evaluate it
as if it is JavaScript.
OK and so Jason originally became popular
because.
You simply say eval and you get the
deserialized version of the object and
but unfortunately as you can't easily
imagine,
there are few security issues around the
ability of eval evaluating whatever you
receive.
And so Jason was designed to say, OK,
the syntax is the JavaScript syntax,
but this is allowed.
The rest is not allowed,
so it's more secure.
And so today's Jason implementation never
used the the eval from JavaScript to work.
And.
Also JSON is made of elements and the
elements is a white space value,
white space and so on and so forth.
And so as you can see also in JavaScript
in in JSON you have elements.
And everything is an element that can be
a list or a dictionary,
and a dictionary is a sequence of key
values, etcetera, etcetera.
We have already at this,
but I think it's a nice exercise to go
through.
Uh, this page because uh,
it's uh entirely the this is the full
definition.
So it's a a nice exercise.
If you want to do an exercise,
you can write adjacent parcel of your own
or you can ask the.
AI to generate one and then you have to
double check that this is compliant with
this technician.
Both are good exercise for the advanced
programming course.
YAML, YAML.
Can you generate an example of YAML?
So.
When you have to write the configuration,
for instance of a network speech,
it's so boring to use curly braces,
codes around the keys,
it's so difficult to read.
Can we get a different syntax?
And the answer is yes,
we can get YAML yet another.
Markup language and and it's like.
So the definition of YAML is like.
There are sections and subsections and
values and and list of values that are
written like dash and like like item of a
bullet list.
Uh.
And where this thing is using the popular
use of this?
Vernet ECS or Docker? Docker compose.
A Docker compose file is basically a YAML
file.
Natus which is are often represent the
configuration are often represented as
YAML file.
So but as you can see at the end of the
day similar idea.
You represent the tree.
What we are looking for is to reduce the
the cost of the annotations.
I mean XML was really heavy in terms of
the annotations, Jason was simpler.
YAMO is is simpler.
Notice that there are data structure that
are difficult to define in YAMO,
but nevertheless that's not the point to
compare this level of things.
Now can you show me?
The an example.
Oh, he's on.
OK.
Uh, compare it to Jason.
I never tried this. Let me see.
If the AI is good enough and up to date.
TSO understands for tokenized Jason, so.
It has been just proposed.
Oh, conceptual. No, I want the syntax.
No, that's not the I had in mind.
Well, OK, let me.
So there is a a T zone that is basically
a binary representation of Jason.
That's not this is not.
Uh, no, I am referring to.
From I in base.
And I hope that I remember the acronym
because I read it few days ago,
so I don't have yet.
Hmm.
I have to find it.
I think I bookmarked it.
This morning.
I hate the.
No, this is the analytics.
Can you believe that after this?
All my videos, uh.
I still struggle to find the.
Part of the information on I will I will
tell you.
I mean I did suspect that this on it's
something like this on.
But.
Can you search for some for something
similar again?
Space recently promoted it as a as a
syntax to reduce token consumption.
I I I memorized the the an an example but.
Oh, can you?
Search.
Search for a different.
Name I may remember are.
Last try, last attempted,
otherwise I stop in it.
So as you can see, so that's interesting.
That's a meta for example when you start
looking with the AI. Now I use the T-son.
T-son is part of the history of the state.
But.
See. OK, I I yeah.
I I clashed in my mind. Uh, these on.
OK. Thank you. Really appreciate so.
As you can see,
this is the tune that the Jason Jason
that I remind.
I remind you that was invented because it
was much simpler than XML,
but now it's too complicated and so this
is the tune version.
This one is so.
Users to ID name role,
one is a license and this version is
clearly more compact and this implies
less token consumed by the the AI.
And this is important. OK,
there is an open specification.
There is a working draft.
And that's it. OK, so now as I promised,
one final the markdown.
Markdown is interesting.
So markdown.
1.
Notepad.
So markdown has become so popular that
Notepad introduces it. This is the title.
And then I have uh uh.
Section.
Baxter.
And and let's say that text is a is a
link to.
Wow. OK.
So.
If I asked to see the syntax,
this is the markdown syntax. OK,
and as you can see,
it still represents implicitly a tree,
but it's a sequential notation, so.
So with some exceptions.
So if you look at at the link,
the link is is the is an element
essentially. OK,
clearly it's not generalized,
it's just for markup or markdown of text.
OK,
so it has no ambition to become a general
syntax or whatever.
But nevertheless it's a markup,
even though they want markdown is a
markup syntax.
But basically there is the so the title
that contains sections etcetera.
And so if I tell you title until there is
another title,
you assume that everything is part of
that title when there is a section and.
Ashes are used to qualify and distinguish
the thing.
Basically all the subsections are
considered children of that section,
etcetera.
So the syntax in this case has no closing
brace because those are implicitly hidden
in the definition of the.
The text itself,
and in this respect I think it's worth
mentioning as someone of you mentioned
mermaid similar idea.
It is a variant of YAML syntax.
And and basically the organisation of the
various elements are hidden.
So clearly there is a point in which you
lose generality in a markup syntax and
you decide as in this this is OK for text
and no no more than that.
But you can stay general enough to
represent trees in many cases,
so as you can see from.
The XML with namespaces down to Jason
down to tune.
You see that there is a lot of room to
improve the syntax we use to represent
structured objects at some.
Cost because the extra notation XML
allowed for globally scalable use of name
which is basically impossible in JSON and
if you want to introduce in JSON.
A similar concept,
you will end up writing it.
Pretty much the same as you did with XML.
So I think that is enough.
I hope you have a better understanding of
markup languages and XML from today.
See you tomorrow.